Preliminary Guide to the of the James Burchell Richardson papers, 1803-1910 and undated, bulk 1822-1910 RL.10037
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Burchell Richardson papers
1803-1910 and undated, bulk 1822-1910
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richardson, James Burchell
RL.10037
3.5 Linear Feet
James Burchell Richardson was a plantation owner, of Sumter District, S.C. This collection contains family letters and business papers of James B. Richardson, plantation owner and slaveholder, and of his descendants. The letters and papers contain references to the allotment of slave labor for road and railroad construction; the impressment of slaves for work on fortifications during the Civil War; political wrangles; James B. and Richard C. Richardson's activities in the Confederate Army; social and economic conditions on South Carolina plantations before, during, and after the Civil War; the postwar depression and poverty in the South; and tenant farming during the postwar period.
Biographical Note
James Burchell Richardson was a plantation owner, of Sumter District, S.C.
Collection Overview
This collection contains family letters and business papers of James B. Richardson, plantation owner and slaveholder, and of his descendants. The letters and papers contain references to the allotment of slave labor for road and railroad construction; the impressment of slaves for work on fortifications during the Civil War; political wrangles; James B. and Richard C. Richardson's activities in the Confederate Army; social and economic conditions on South Carolina plantations before, during, and after the Civil War; the postwar depression and poverty in the South; and tenant farming during the postwar period.
Provenance
The James Burchell Richardson papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1939-1940.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
United States -- Politics and government; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives; Southern States -- Economic conditions; Farm tenancy -- South Carolina; South Carolina -- Social life and customs; South Carolina -- Politics and government; Slavery -- South Carolina; Plantations -- South Carolina; Richardson, James Burchell; Richardson family; Confederate States of America. Army -- Military life
- James Burchell Richardson papers, 1803-1910 and undated, bulk 1822-1910
  - Correspondence, 1822-1858 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1859-1885 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1886-1910 and undated (Box 3)
  - Financial Papers, 1819-1849 (Box 4)
  - Financial Papers, 1850-1887 (Box 5)
  - Financial Papers, 1888-1909 and undated (Box 6)
  - Account Books, 1834-1903 (Box 6)
  - Account Books, 1894-1897 (Box 7)
  - Legal Papers, 1803-1909 and undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 7)